Finding Aid for Wilbert J. McKeachie Papers 1941-1991
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Wilbert J. McKeachie papers
1941-1991
1960-1991
McKeachie, Wilbert James, 1921-
Professor of psychology at the University of Michigan, director of the university's Center for Research on Learning and Teaching. Papers include two subgroups, Psychology and Center for Research on Learning and Teaching. The Psychology subgroup includes American Psychological Association files, correspondence, course materials, speeches, and topical files. The CRLT subgroup includes correspondence, course materials and topical files.
921087 Aa 2
8.5 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The collection (Donor # 8017 ) was donated in March 1992.
The collection is open for research.
Wilbert J. McKeachie, a professor of psychology at the University of Michigan highly regarded for both his teaching and research on teaching, was born in 1921 in Clarkston, Michigan. He won a scholarship to Michigan State Normal College (now Eastern Michigan University), where he majored in mathematics and minored in English and history. He graduated with a BA in 1942, shortly after America's entry into World War II. Troubled by the moral justification for the war and undecided as to whether he should become a conscientious objector or be drafted, McKeachie took a job, offered him by a friend, as minister of two Methodist churches in the Upper Peninsula. When the draft board turned down his request for deferment as a minister, McKeachie enlisted in the Navy in the Fall of 1942 and served for the duration of the war as a radar and communications officer on a destroyer in the Pacific.
McKeachie's interest in psychology dated from the time he read an article on psychology as a vocation when he was fourteen. His interest continued to grow through the years and in 1945, after leaving the Navy, he enrolled at the University of Michigan in the MA program in clinical psychology. After completing the MA program, he pursued a PhD which he earned in 1949. McKeachie's interest in carrying out research on teaching and learning was sparked by his participation as a teaching fellow in the introductory psychology course taught by Harold Guetzkow. "In that role, he and a splendid cadre of teaching fellows thrashed out issues of teaching goals, methods, and pragmatics and were pressed by Guetzkow toward empirical answers to their questions about teaching effectiveness. His interest in research in teaching was heightened by his role as coordinator for the introductory course's research projects and extended into his doctoral research exploring social-psychological factors in college classrooms." (Box 4, Folder: Biographical #2, "Awards for Distinguished Education and Training Contributions: 1987").
McKeachie began his professional affiliation with the University of Michigan shortly after receiving his doctorate, when he was offered a position with the department and assumed responsibility for introductory psychology. In addition he redesigned both the undergraduate and graduate curriculums. He continued with his research and in the following years became internationally known for his work "exploring student motivation, the interaction of personality variables and teaching methods, cognitive and learning analyses of classroom teaching, students' perceptions of teachers and teaching, and evaluation of teaching effectiveness." (Ibid). Teaching Tips, one of his most important publications, grew out of his research and his experience in working with teaching assistants in the introductory psychology course. It has been used by thousands of beginning college teachers and according to McKeachie, "has given me the most satisfaction of anything I have written." (Box 4, Folder: Biographical #2, "Autobiography for Krawiec, T.S.")
McKeachie rapidly moved through the ranks at the university to become professor of psychology, and in 1961 began a ten-year tenure as chairman of the department. In recalling the most important aspects of his chairmanship, McKeachie explains, "We had already pioneered in social psychology, mathematical psychology, and clinical psychology. During my years as chairman we continued to produce outstanding students in these fields and built on the foundations laid by Marquis and Kelly in human information processing, brain and behavior, organizational psychology, and school psychology. We developed new programs in developmental psychology, community psychology, psychopharmacology and psycholinguistics....One of the most satisfying achievements of the Department during the years of my chairmanship was our leadership in training Black psychologists." (Box 4, Folder: Biographical #2, "Autobiography for Krawiec, T. S.")
While serving as department chairman, McKeachie helped establish the Center for Research on Learning and Teaching (CRLT), one of the first centers of its kind in the country. He later served as its director for eight years from 1975 to 1983. Thereafter his time spent on teaching and research was divided between the Department of Psychology and CRLT. Although he formally retired in 1992, McKeachie continues to teach various classes.
Throughout his forty-two years at the University of Michigan, McKeachie served on a variety of departmental, college, and university-wide committees, boards, and task forces. He chaired the Committee on Student Opinion of Courses and Teaching, served on the Committee on the Program in Religion, chaired the [LSA] College Committee on Curriculum, which recommended and helped plan the establishment of the Residential College, served on the Budget Priorities Committee, chaired the LSA Steering Committee on Admissions, and was elected chairman of the University Faculty Senate and president of the local chapter of the American Association of University Professors. His interest in athletics (he is famous around the university and in the profession for his softball pitching skills) is reflected in his membership on the Senate Committee on Athletic Policy and on the Board in Control of Intercollegiate Athletics. In addition, he served on many search committees, including the one which led to the hiring of Robben Fleming as university president in 1967.
McKeachie has been quite active professionally, especially in the American Psychological Association (APA) for which he served as president in 1976. He has also been president of the American Association of Higher Education and has served in leadership roles in the American Council on Education, the American Education Research Association (AERA), the International Union of Psychological Science, the International Association of Applied Psychology, the Conference of State Psychological Associations, and the Michigan Psychological Association.
Because of his skills as a teacher and the quality of his research, McKeachie has been the recipient of a number of awards from professional organizations, including the AERA, APA, and American Psychological Foundation. He has also received the Alumni Award for Distinguished Teaching and the Distinguished Faculty Governance Award from the University of Michigan. Honorary degrees have been awarded him by the University of Cincinnati, Denison University, Eastern Michigan University, Hope College, and Northwestern University.
Religion has long played an important part in McKeachie's life and has influenced his career as a professor of psychology (one of the earliest classes he taught at the university was Psychology and Religion). He and his wife, Ginny (formerly Virginia Mack), have been active members of the First Baptist Church of Ann Arbor for over forty years. McKeachie met Ginny when he was a senior in college; they were married shortly before he enlisted in the Navy in the Fall of 1942. They have two children.
The Wilbert J. McKeachie papers are comprised of two subgroups: Psychology and CRLT. The subgroups reflect the distinctions in McKeachie's roles at the university. The materials in the Psychology subgroup were removed from McKeachie's office in the Department of Psychology; the materials in the CRLT subgroup came from his office in the Center. The Psychology subgroup, the larger of the two, is divided into five series: the American Psychological Association, Correspondence, Course Materials, Speeches, and Topical. The CRLT subgroup is divided into four series: Correspondence, Course Materials, Speeches, and Topical. The subgroup and series organization of the papers is identical to the organizational system used by McKeachie when he maintained the files. Because of the similarity in time span and content of the series with the same headings, however, especially correspondence, course materials, and speeches, the researcher is advised to consult both subgroups when studying a particular topic or facet of McKeachie's career.
Subjects:
American Psychological Association.; Learning, Psychology of.; Psychology.; Teaching.; University of Michigan--Sports.; University of Michigan. Board in Control of Intercollegiate Athletics.; University of Michigan. Center for Research on Learning and Teaching.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Psychology.; University of Michigan--Faculty.
- Psychology
  - American Psychological Association
    The American Psychological Association series (4 folders) contains materials related to searches, especially the one held in 1984-1985, for a new executive director of the organization. The files include evaluations and notes on candidates, search process summaries and reports, correspondence, and candidate vitae. (The bulk of the materials documenting McKeachie's activities in the APA are in the APA collection in the Library of Congress.)
    - Executive Officer Searches, 1975-1987; 4 folders (Box 1)
  - Correspondence
    The Correspondence series (.75 linear feet) contains both incoming and outgoing correspondence, mostly with other psychologists. It is arranged by letter of the alphabet, and within letter, chronologically by year and month. The correspondence is primarily from 1970 to 1991, and covers a variety of professional matters, including research projects, meetings and workshops and their outcomes, professional organization matters, and includes discussions of books and articles. Although the correspondence is often brief, it is a valuable source for studying intellectual exchanges between McKeachie and his peers around the country.
    - A-Z, 24 folders (Box 1)
  - Course Materials
    The Course Materials series (1 linear foot) is arranged alphabetically by course title. The materials include syllabi, course objectives, examinations and quizzes, and lectures. The latter are often in outline form but some are in text form. The Writings found in the Psychology and Religion files are on a variety of topics and include lectures and notes from talks.
    - General Psychology (Psychology 31), undated, 1941-1961 (Box 1)
    - Introduction to Psychology (Psychology 172), 1972-1974 (Box 1)
    - Introduction to Psychology as a Natural Science (Psychology 170)
      - General, 1989 (Box 1)
      - Lectures, 1971-1975 (Box 1)
    - Learning to Learn (Psychology 100)
      - General
        - 1982-1987 (Box 1)
        - 1988-1991 (Box 1)
      - Lectures, 1983-1991 (Box 1)
    - Proseminar (Psychology 600), 1987-1990 (Box 1)
    - Psychology and Religion
      - Courses
        - Psychology 55
          - General, 1952-1969 (Box 1)
          - Examinations, 1952-1960 (Box 1)
        - Psychology 270, 1962-1965 (Box 1)
        - Psychology 370, 1969-1973 (Box 1)
      - Writings (lectures, notes)
        - The Church, undated, 1952 (Box 2)
        - Conversion, 1960-1961 (Box 2)
        - Individual Religious Belief, undated, 1965 (Box 2)
        - Magic, Ritual, Symbol, undated (Box 2)
        - Ministers' Wives, undated, 1958-1959 (Box 2)
        - Mysticism and Prophecy, 1950-1973 (Box 2)
        - Personal Beliefs, undated, 1950-1960 (Box 2)
        - The Physical Nature of Man, undated (Box 2)
        - Protestant Reformation, undated (Box 2)
        - Religion and Culture, undated (Box 2)
        - Religion and Mental Health, undated, 1960-1973 (Box 2)
        - Social Factors in Religion, undated, 1952 (Box 2)
      - Psychology of Aging (Psychology 459), 1976-1982; 3 folders (Box 2)
  - Speeches
    The Speeches series (1.5 linear feet) is arranged alphabetically by topic and within topic, alphabetically by title. Within many of the folders, the researcher will find versions of the speech from different years. The series is the most informative one for studying McKeachie's philosophy of and views on teaching and learning.
    - Church
      - The Nature of the University and the Church, 1969 (Box 3)
      - A Saint For Our Times: LeRoy Waterman, 1981 (Box 3)
      - Scientific Psychology and Religion, undated (Box 3)
    - Curriculum
      - Expectancy Concepts in the First Course, undated, 1957 (Box 3)
      - Field Experience in the Psychology Curriculum, 1969 (Box 3)
      - The Ingredients of a Good Undergraduate Education, 1987 (Box 3)
      - On Post-Baccalaureate Education, undated (Box 3)
      - A Philosophy for the First Course in Psychology, 1970 (Box 3)
      - Research Training in the Graduate Curriculum, 1957 (Box 3)
      - The Responsibility of Graduate Schools: Are We Cutting Off Our Nose To Spite Our Face?, 1961 (Box 3)
      - Teaching Psychology of Today From A Developmental Point of View, 1979 (Box 3)
      - Undergraduate Curriculum in a Large University, 1972 (Box 3)
      - Undergraduate Psychology in the, 1970s; 1971 (Box 3)
    - Department Chairman
      - Academic Responsibility: The Department Chairman's View, 1972 (Box 3)
      - Administrative Decision Making Regarding Teaching, 1985 (Box 3)
      - The Department Chairman, 1970 (Box 3)
      - How Administrators Can Improve Teaching, undated, 1991 (Box 3)
      - The Role of Administrators in Faculty Development, 1985; 1988 (Box 3)
      - The Role of Department Chairmen in Faculty Evaluation, 1971-1979 (Box 3)
    - Faculty/Faculty Development
      - Are Teachers Inefficient?, undated (Box 3)
      - Balancing Career Demands, undated, 1981-1982 (Box 3)
      - Changing Teacher Behavior to Improve Instruction, undated (Box 3)
      - Enhancing Intrinsic Rewards of Teaching, undated, 1992 (Box 3)
      - Faculty, undated, 1985 (Box 3)
      - Faculty Development and Evaluation, 1990-1991 (Box 3)
      - The Faculty: Who They Are, What They Do, 1969; 1991 (Box 3)
      - The Importance of Professional Growth and Development, 1981; 1988 (Box 3)
      - Improving/Motivating Teaching, 1985 (Box 3)
      - Improving the Quality of Faculty Development and Evaluation, 1980 (Box 3)
      - Learning Teaching and Learning from Teaching, 1989 (Box 3)
      - The Michigan Faculty, 1971 (Box 3)
      - Motivating Faculty and Students, 1990 (Box 3)
      - Motivating Students, Faculty, or Ourselves, 1987 (Box 3)
      - Rewards of Teaching, 1974; 1983 (Box 3)
      - The State of the Art in Improving Learning and Teaching, 1977 (Box 3)
      - What Theories Underlie The Practice of Faculty Development, 1990 (Box 3)
    - Faculty Evaluation
      - Correlates of Student Ratings, 1973 (Box 3)
      - Current Findings on the Reliability and Validity of Student Evaluations of Teaching, 1974 (Box 3)
      - Evaluating Teaching, 1970-1991 (Box 3)
      - Evaluating Teaching: Student Ratings, 1991 (Box 3)
      - Instructional Evaluation, 1985 (Box 3)
      - Peer Evaluation of Teaching, 1985; 1991 (Box 3)
      - Where Have We Been? Where Do We Go From Here?, undated, 1985 (Box 3)
    - Psychology
      - Careers in Psychology, 1965 (Box 3)
      - Functions of the Medical Model, 1967 (Box 3)
      - Future Directions for Psychology-the Perspectives from APA, 1976 (Box 3)
      - Graduate Education in Psychology: The Many Lives of the Graduate Student, undated (Box 3)
      - Graduate Work in Psychology, undated, 1964-1988 (Box 3)
      - The Place of the Psychology Department and the State Association in Psychology, 1971 (Box 3)
      - Prospects for Prospective Psychologists, 1976 (Box 3)
      - Psychology:, 1895-1975; 1975 (Box 3)
      - Psychology and Public Affairs, 1969 (Box 3)
      - Psychology: Are We One or Many?, 1976 (Box 3)
      - Psychology in the Bicentennial Year, 1976 (Box 3)
      - Psychology Today and in the 1978,1981, 1980s (Box 3)
      - State Associations: A View from the Board (of directors of the APA), undated (Box 3)
    - Research
      - Achievement Anxiety, Learning Strategies, and Achievement, undated, 1982-1986 (Box 3)
      - Afterthoughts on Chapter 23 of AERA Handbook, 1966 (Box 3)
      - Applications of Cognitive Psychology to Teaching and Learning, 1985 (Box 3)
      - Assessing Research Achievements, undated (Box 3)
      - Characteristics of Effective Teachers: Some Research Results, 1966 (Box 3)
      - Cognitive Psychology and Education, 1986 (Box 3)
      - Conceptual Fragmentation, 1985 (Box 3)
      - Contemporary Instructional Psychology and Educational Practice, 1985 (Box 3)
      - Contemporary Issues in Psychology and Higher Education, 1986 (Box 3)
      - Contemporary Psychology and College Teaching, undated, 1979; 1981 (Box 3)
      - Current Trends in Scientific and Professional Psychology, 1978 (Box 3)
      - The Decline and Fall of the Laws of Learning, 1973 (Box 3)
      - Has the Psychology of Instruction Progressed in This Century?, 1976 (Box 3)
      - Instructional Psychology in Higher Education, undated, 1982 (Box 3)
      - Interaction in the Classroom: Interpersonal and Statistical, 1973-1978 (Box 3)
      - Learning to Learn, 1983; 1984 (Box 3)
      - Motivation, Teaching Methods, and College Learning, 1961-1968 (Box 3)
      - New Directions-Another View, 1972 (Box 3)
      - New Teaching Methods: Panaceas or Placebos?, 1961 (Box 3)
      - The Past, Present, and Future of Educational and Instructional Psychology, 1986 (Box 3)
      - The Perils of Replicating: Motivation, Teaching Methods, and Student Learning, 1964 (Box 3)
      - Qualitative Studies of College Teaching and Learning, 1984 (Box 3)
      - Quality and Equality in Education, 1980 (Box 3)
    - Teaching
      - Applying Cognitive and Motivational Psychology to Improving Teaching, 1991 (Box 3)
      - Approaches to Undergraduate Teaching, 1987 (Box 3)
      - Assessing Growth in Thinking in College Courses, 1988 (Box 3)
      - Classroom Research, undated (Box 3)
      - Classroom Techniques and Principles of Learning, undated (Box 3)
      - Cognitive Psychology and Education, 1986 (Box 3)
      - College Student Development, 1975 (Box 3)
      - The College Teacher and Creativity, undated (Box 3)
      - Comparison of Different Teaching and Learning Methods, 1969 (Box 3)
      - Contemporary Psychology and College Teaching, undated (Box 3)
      - Current Trends in Learning and Teaching, 1978 (Box 3)
      - Defining the Components of Teaching, undated (Box 3)
      - Developing Excellence in College Teaching, undated (Box 3)
      - Effective College Teaching, Can Research Help?, 1974 (Box 3)
      - Effective College Teaching: Current Trends in Psychology, 1975 (Box 3)
      - Effective Methods of Teaching and Lecturing, 1972-1984 (Box 3)
      - Effective Teaching, 1961-1990 (Box 3)
      - Effective Teaching: The Relevance of the Curriculum, 1966 (Box 3)
      - Eight Ways to Improve Instruction, 1985 (Box 3)
      - Essential Components of Effective Instruction, 1989 (Box 3)
      - Evaluation of Learning and Teaching, 1960; 1972 (Box 3)
      - Excellence in Teaching, 1984 (Box 3)
      - Facilitating Teaching and Learning, 1977 (Box 3)
      - Five Ways to Improve Instruction, 1986; 1988 (Box 3)
      - Getting Students to Think, 1989; 1991 (Box 3)
      - How Do Students Learn?, undated (Box 3)
      - Improving Education, 1991 (Box 3)
      - Improving Teaching, 1986 (Box 3)
      - Increasing Students' Cognitive Skills and Motivation for Learning, 1990 (Box 3)
      - Instructional Psychology and Educational Practice, 1985 (Box 3)
      - Learning and Teaching, undated, 1977; 1985 (Box 3)
      - Learning in a Problem-Based Setting, 1987 (Box 3)
      - Learning, Motivation, and Teaching, 1961-1968 (Box 3)
      - Learning, Thinking, and Thorndike, 1988 (Box 3)
      - Learning Theory and College Teaching, undated (Box 3)
      - Lecturing, undated, 1984; 1985 (Box 4)
      - Matching Means with Ends in Teaching, undated (Box 4)
      - Matching Technology with the Needs of Students, 1984 (Box 4)
      - Motivating Students, 1968-1989 (Box 4)
      - Motivation and Learning, 1962-1991 (Box 4)
      - Motivation, Cognition, and College Teaching, 1980-1990 (Box 4)
      - Multiple Roles of the Instructor, 1987 (Box 4)
      - Personalizing College Teaching, 1967; 1968 (Box 4)
      - Physicians as Teachers, 1978 (Box 4)
      - Psychology and Adult Cognition, 1987 (Box 4)
      - Recent Research in Student Learning and How It Can Be Used in the Classroom, 1986-1991 (Box 4)
      - Recent Research on University Learning and Teaching, 1991; 1992 (Box 4)
      - Reflections on Instructional Effectiveness, 1987 (Box 4)
      - Relation of Learning Theory to Classroom Instruction, 1970 (Box 4)
      - Research on College Teaching, 1967-1986 (Box 4)
      - Role of Testing in Student Learning, 1983 (Box 4)
      - Stimulating Active Learning, undated, 1990 (Box 4)
      - Strategies for Teaching, undated (Box 4)
      - Student Learning, undated, 1976 (Box 4)
      - Teachers and Technology In Higher Education, 1967 (Box 4)
      - Teaching and Learning, undated, 1988-1990 (Box 4)
      - Teaching and Research on Teaching, 1989 (Box 4)
      - Teaching and Learning: Kindergarten Through College, 1987 (Box 4)
      - Teaching and Technology, 1989 (Box 4)
      - Teaching Cognitive Psychology, 1987 (Box 4)
      - Teaching Content and Teaching Thinking, 1988 (Box 4)
      - Teaching for Active Learning and Student Diversity in Large Classes, undated (Box 4)
      - Teaching in a University, 1966 (Box 4)
      - The Teaching-Learning Process: Teaching, 1970 (Box 4)
      - Teaching Methods in the University, 1966 (Box 4)
      - Teaching Psychology, undated, 1987 (Box 4)
      - Teaching Psychology to Undergraduates, 1978 (Box 4)
      - Teaching Scientific Psychology in the Denominational College, undated (Box 4)
      - Teaching Students To Be More Strategic Learners and Thinkers, undated, 1984-1988 (Box 4)
      - Teaching Thinking and Reasoning, 1987; 1991 (Box 4)
      - Television and Education, 1979 (Box 4)
      - Thinking, 1989 (Box 4)
      - Toward More Effective Presentation: Classroom Techniques and Principles of Learning, 1962; 1965 (Box 4)
      - Understanding the Student, undated (Box 4)
      - The University as a Community of Learners, 1964-1983 (Box 4)
      - Varieties of Excellence in College Teaching, 1989 (Box 4)
      - What College Teachers Need to Know About Psychological Processes, undated, 1950 (Box 4)
      - What Do We Mean By Good Teaching?, 1988; 1989 (Box 4)
      - What Teachers Need to Know, undated (Box 4)
      - What We Know About College Learning and Teaching, 1972; 1978 (Box 4)
      - What Research Says About Effective and Ineffective Teaching Practices in the College Classroom, 1979 (Box 4)
    - Teaching Assistant (TA) Training
      - The Teaching Assistant Experience, undated (Box 4)
      - Training College Teachers, undated, 1960-1963 (Box 4)
    - Miscellaneous
      - A Challenge to Change, 1979 (Box 4)
      - Are There Any Bright Spots in the Gloom of Budget Cuts?, undated (Box 4)
      - The College Culture, 1962 (Box 4)
      - Holly High School, undated (Box 4)
      - The Impact of NTL on the Theory and Practice of Learning, 1976 (Box 4)
      - The School Year Begins, 1961 (Box 4)